Guide to the Cecile Starr Papers Relating to Mary Ellen Bute
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Cecile Starr papers relating to Mary Ellen Bute
1935-2008
GEN MSS 679
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.09
(11 boxes)
The Cecile Starr Papers Relating to Mary Ellen Bute consist of Starr's research files on the filmmaker Mary Ellen Bute and audiovisual recordings of and about Bute. The papers document Starr's research and fundraising to produce a documentary film about Bute (never completed) as well as Starr's work to publicize and distribute Bute's films, especially after Bute's death.
Starr, Cecile
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Cecile Starr on the Edith and Richard French Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 9-11 (Audiovisual formats): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Cecile Starr (1921-)
Filmmaker, critic, and producer Cecile Starr was born July 14, 1921 in Nashville, Tennessee. She studied film at Columbia University, where she taught from 1955-1961. She has worked as a consultant and educational coordinator for the Lincoln Center, the New School for Social Research, Hunter College, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and the United Nations World Health Organization. She married film producer Aram Boyajian in 1957.
Mary Ellen Bute, 1906-1983
Mary Ellen Bute was a film animator, director and producer. She was a pioneer in adopting electronic techniques for film animation. Early in her career she made animated films in the "visual music" style that synchronized abstract images and music. Her later films were live action and included adaptations of works by James Joyce and Thornton Wilder.
Bute was born in Houston, Texas in 1906. She studied painting at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts in Philadephia and lighting design at Yale University. Her early influences included Leon Theremin and Gerald Warburg and she collaborated with Theremin to produce a paper titled "Light as an art material and its possible synchronization with sound" (1932). Most of Bute's films were produced by Ted Nemeth Studios or Expanding Cinema Studios and her collaborators included Norman McLaren and Melville Webber. Later in life Bute was a founding member of the Women's Independent Film Exchange.
Bute's films include: "Synchromy" (1932 or 1933), "Rhythm in Light" (1934), "Synchromy No. 2" (1935), "Dada" (1936), "Parabola" (1937), "Escape" (1937), "Spook Sport" (1939), "Tarantella" (1940), "Polka Graph" (1947), "Color Rhapsody" (1948), "Imagination" (1948), "New Sensations in Sound" (1949), "Pastorale" (1950), "Abstronic" (1952), "Mood Contrasts" (1953), "The Boy Who Saw Through" (1956, producer), "Passages from James Joyce's Finnegan's Wake" (1965-1967), and "Out of the Cradle Endlessly Rocking" (1977-1980, unfinished). Bute's projects also include two adaptations of plays: "Lazarus Laughed" by Eugene O'Neill and "Skin of Our Teeth" by Thornton Wilder (both unfinished).
In 1940 Bute married camera operator and painter Theodore (Ted) Nemeth and they collaborated on many of her projects. Ted Nemeth Studios focused on commercial films and Nemeth also handled the distribution of Bute's films. Bute and Nemeth had two sons: Theodore Jr. and James.
Scope and Contents
The Cecile Starr Papers Relating to Mary Ellen Bute consist of Starr's research files on the filmmaker Mary Ellen Bute and audiovisual recordings of and about Bute. The papers document Starr's research and fundraising to produce a documentary film about Bute (never completed) as well as Starr's work to publicize and distribute Bute's films, especially after Bute's death.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Research Files, 1935-2008. II. Audio Recordings, 1976-2006. III. Video Recordings, 1977-1999.
Cinematographers; Motion picture producers and directors; Independent filmmakers; Motion pictures; Women motion picture producers and directors; Filmmakers; Starr, Cecile; Bute, Mary Ellen
- Research Files, 1935-2008; Series I; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged as received by the Beinecke Library.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of Starr's research files on Mary Ellen Bute. Files include correspondence (incoming and copies of outgoing), drafts of writings, copies of printed material, and notes. The topics of the material relate to Mary Ellen Bute, Starr's research on Bute (especially Starr's planned documentary film on Bute), and Starr's work to publicize and distribute Bute's films.
  - Bute, Mary Ellen, 1952-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nemeth, Ted, 1945-2008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Boyd, Rutherford, 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bruguière, Francis, Light Rhythm, 1977-2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dockum, Charles, 2004-2007, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gengaro, Christine Lee, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Production of documentary on Bute, 1996-2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fundraising for documentary on Bute, 1987-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hollander, David, 2000-2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hall, Wendy Jackson, 1994-2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Kudláček, Martina, 2003-2008 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Leger, Jackie, 1990-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Muskat, Lisa, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Shamash, Jessica, 1999-2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Other possible filmmakers, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Naumann, Sandra, 2005-2008 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - University of Minnesota, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - University of Wisconsin, 1992-2007 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Interviews with Bute and with others about Bute, 1984-2002, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lion, Margo, 1990-2007 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Moritz, William, 1996-2002 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Posner, Bruce, 1995-2006 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Schoonmaker, Thelma, 1996-2007 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Basquin, Kit, 1994-2006 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Basquin, Kit (continued), 1984-1999 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Mollot, Larry, 1987-2006 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Mary Ellen Bute: Expanding Cinema (planned documentary on Bute), script, draft and notes (copy), undated (Box 3, Folder 30-32)
  - Note cards, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Essay for Notable American Women, drafts, correspondence and notes, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Women's Film Preservation Fund, 1998-2007 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Bute prints and preservation, 1998-2007 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Bute holdings, 1995-2006 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Pike, Angeline. Creative Film Society, 1992-2006 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Yale University, 1987-2008 (Box 4, Folder 39-40)
  - Bute film copyrights, 1990-1998 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Finnegans Wake, 1999-2008, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Finnegans Wake. U.S. rentals, 1982-2002 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Finnegans Wake. Foreign rentals, 1996-2001 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Finnegans Wake. Gerry Fialka, 2004-2008 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Bute in films of others, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Bute in magazines and newspapers, 1981-2003 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Bute in books, 2005, undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Bute promotion. Television, 1977-1994 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Bute "Dope sheet." BBC television program, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - General correspondence, 1982-2008 (Box 5, Folder 51-52)
  - Canada, 2001-2006 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Bute rentals. Shorts, 1990-2004 (Box 5, Folder 54-56)
  - Bute rentals. Shorts. Europe, 1991-2004 (Box 5, Folder 57-58)
  - Short abstract films, 1988-2002 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - London. Sketch Gallery, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Programs, 2000-2008 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Women's Independent Film Exchange, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Bute promotion. Foreign, 1994-1998 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Institute of Media Archaeology, 2006-2007 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Stephanie Maxwell. European tour, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Programs, 1990-2008 (Box 6, Folder 66-73)
- Audio Recordings, 1976-2006; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series II is arranged as received by the Beinecke Library.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audio recordings are stored in Restricted Fragile. Use copies may be requested. Please consult with Access Services for more information.
  Series II consists of 1/8-inch audio cassette recordings of interviews and events relating to Mary Ellen Bute. Folder descriptions are based on information on the cassettes and cases.
  - Camera Three. Finnegans Wake, undated; (30 minutes) (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Virginia Gibbs Smyth interview about Mary Ellen Bute by Kit Smith Basquin, 1984 August 11 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Cecile Starr. Joyce Society. Donnell Library, undated (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - BBC "Dope sheet", undated (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Cecile Starr interview with Barbara Moss at Donnell Library. Cecile Starr talk at Donnell, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Cecile Starr. Cooper Union, 1989 October 18 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Mary Ellen Bute speaks at the Chicago Art Institute on self and films, 1976 May 7 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Bute, Grant, Starr. Am. Film Festival, 1979 June (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Thelma Schoonmaker. Margo Lion, undated (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Ted Nemeth, Bruce Posner, Cecile Starr on Bute, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 83-84)
  - Doris Chase. Hilary Harris. Gordon Hitchens, undated (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Ted Nemeth reading Mary Ellen Bute's biography and Ted Jr.'s Finnegans Wake statement, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - William Moritz. Bruce Posner, undated (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - University of Southern California screening of Passages from James Joyce's Finnegans Wake, 2006 November 16 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    Includes remarks by Peter Haskell and panel discussion with Peter Haskell, Gerry Fialka and Cindy Keefer.
- Video Recordings, 1977-1999; Series III; 1.34; (2 boxes)
  Series III is arranged as received by the Beinecke Library.
  Original video recordings are stored in Restricted Fragile. Use copies may be requested. Please consult with Access Services for more information.
  Series III consists of VHS tape recordings of interviews, broadcasts and demos relating to Mary Ellen Bute. Folder descriptions are based on information on the cassettes and cases.
  - Camera Three, Women in Film, Part III, and Finnegans Wake, Buffalo, 1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Women in Film, Part II, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Dope Sheet. Series #3, 1999 October; (28 minutes, 50 seconds) (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Demo reel by Muskat. Rough cut. Not accepted, 1998 March 20; circa 5 minutes (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Zack Bowen and Philip Lyman, undated (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Page Johnson, Philip Lyman and Larry Kardish, undated (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - John Bute in Houston, undated (Box 8, Folder 95-96)
  - Interview with Thelma Schoonmaker. Unedited, undated (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - Stoney, Jacobs and Mekas, undated (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - William Moritz and Bruce Posner, undated (Box 8, Folder 99-100)
  - Bute documentary demo, undated; (13 minutes) (Box 8, Folder 101)
- Restricted Fragile Material
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Box 7 (Box 9, Folder 102-116)
  - Box 8, folders 89-98 (Box 10, Folder 117-126)
  - Box 8, folders 99-101 (Box 11, Folder 127-129)